<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xwikidoc>
  <web>Community</web>
  <name>BrowserSupportStrategy</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <parent>Community.SupportStrategy</parent>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <customClass/>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <creationDate>1319809194000</creationDate>
  <date>1360950280000</date>
  <contentUpdateDate>1354179678000</contentUpdateDate>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>Browser Support Strategy</title>
  <template/>
  <defaultTemplate/>
  <validationScript/>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.0</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <content>There are a lot of browsers out there and supporting them all in all versions is just too hard to be done in a quality manner.

By "supporting" we mean:

* issues created for these browsers in JIRA are not closed as ##won't fix## and we make a best effort to fix them
* we include these browsers in our tests (be them automated or manual)
* when we create new features or modify existing features we make a best effort to verify that they work on the supported list of browsers

The complete and precise list of browsers supported in a given XWiki release is indicated in the [[Release Notes&gt;&gt;xwiki:ReleaseNotes.WebHome]] for that release (starting with XE 3.2).

= Supported Browsers =

|=Browser|=Reason for supporting it|=Notes
|(((
{{browser name="iexplorer" version="8.x"/}}
)))|Currently IE8 has the largest market share of all IEs and it is widely used in enterprise environments.|\\
|(((
{{browser name="iexplorer" version="9.x"/}}
)))|IE9 is slowly getting ground in front of IE8|Support for it started in XE 3.3
|(((
{{browser name="firefox" version="4+"/}}
)))|We support **only** the latest stable Firefox release, since FF4+ have automatic upgrades.|\\
|(((
{{browser name="chrome" version="13+"/}}
)))|We support **only** the latest stable version Chrome release, similar to our FF4+ support.|\\
|(((
{{browser name="safari" version="5"/}}
)))|Reasonable market share|Support for it started in XE 3.3

= Browsers that are not supported =

|=Browser|=Reason for not supporting it|=Starting with
|(((
{{browser name="iexplorer" version="6.x"/}}
)))|(((
* it allows us to use newer technologies which are more useful,
* we can remove lots of hacks we've accumulated over the years
* we have more time to work on more relevant browser versions. A lot of products have also dropped support for IE6 and it was time we did it too!
)))|XE 3.3M1
|(((
{{browser name="iexplorer" version="7.x"/}}
)))|Currently, IE7's market share is similar to the one of IE6. They are both considered obsolete browsers for the same reasons as IE6|XE 3.3M1
|(((
{{browser name="opera" version=""/}}
)))|We don't officially support Opera. This means that we don't test against it all the time, we don't ensure that new features work on it, but if someone raises an issue in jira and it's easy to fix (or if someone provides a patch) then we fix it.|\\
|(((
{{browser name="firefox" version="3.6"/}}
)))|Mozilla ended the support of Firefox 3.6 and they now automatically offer the possibility to update to the latest version of Firefox| XE 4.1 M1
|     Others|Same strategy as Opera above|\\</content>
</xwikidoc>
