<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xwikidoc>
  <web>Design</web>
  <name>EasyXWikiFindings</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <parent>Design.ImproveXWikiUserExperience</parent>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <customClass/>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <creationDate>1253117101000</creationDate>
  <date>1361190322000</date>
  <contentUpdateDate>1361190322000</contentUpdateDate>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>Easy XWiki</title>
  <template/>
  <defaultTemplate/>
  <validationScript/>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.0</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <object>
    <class>
      <name>XWiki.TagClass</name>
      <customClass/>
      <customMapping/>
      <defaultViewSheet/>
      <defaultEditSheet/>
      <defaultWeb/>
      <nameField/>
      <validationScript/>
      <tags>
        <cache>0</cache>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayType>input</displayType>
        <multiSelect>1</multiSelect>
        <name>tags</name>
        <number>1</number>
        <prettyName>Tags</prettyName>
        <relationalStorage>1</relationalStorage>
        <separator>|</separator>
        <separators>|,</separators>
        <size>30</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <values/>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StaticListClass</classType>
      </tags>
    </class>
    <name>Design.EasyXWikiFindings</name>
    <number>0</number>
    <className>XWiki.TagClass</className>
    <guid>339ab231-f7ac-42b4-bc7d-2bc4312b0035</guid>
    <property>
      <tags>
        <value>ux</value>
        <value>usability</value>
      </tags>
    </property>
  </object>
  <content>
= Easy XWiki =

{{toc/}}

Here is a summary of what people said about making XWiki Enterprise easier to use.

{{warning}}
Work in Progress
{{/warning}}

== User Interface ==

=== Dashboard ===

==== Spaces ====

* Give more information about each space
* Use the title of the space's homepage as a title for the whole space
* Create space descriptors?

==== Recent Changes ====

* There should be no changes displayed when starting a new wiki
* Since a new wiki has had no activity going on, why are some modifications displayed?
* System page modifications should be hidden for normal users

==== Tag Cloud ====

* The tag cloud is hidden at the bottom of the list of spaces and hard to see

=== Page Actions ===

We should have only information available from the view mode, not stuff scattered all around the place, the user should be able to see 3 main things:

* where am I?
* what am I doing?
* what can I do?

Things should be easily answered by looking at the page. Right now we do not have a functional model that encompasses all this.

==== Action bar ====

* move the action bar (edit, show, watch...) closer to page content
* shortcuts should be described in the action menu
* use icons in the action bar to make it easier to understand
* splitting the action bar between local and global actions and create 2 menus
** global one -&gt; administration, create new content, manage watchlist
** page menu -&gt; actions related to the current page

==== Logged-in / Logged-out ====

* When not logged-in -&gt; edit action is hidden
** display the edit action as disabled to let people know it's a wiki
** on a public website you don't want to see the action bar for guests anyway

==== Page creation ====

* streamline the link creation process -&gt; make it faster, more simple
** make document information more visible
* page creation panel on the right side that isn't good
** when in the blog interface, it duplicates the creation panel (context issue)
** should be a button
** where is the page created? which other pages is the created page related to?
** all create actions made contextual to the wiki (from treeview, from wikilinks)
* add tags, categories when creating a page

=== Titles ===

* page title issue -&gt; name vs title, it's confusing
* use document titles instead of page names as much as possible
** uniform name management when creating new pages

=== Avatars ===

* comments lack the user avatar
* make user avatars easy to use (macro)

=== Other ===

* too much information in search results, in the dashboard -&gt; when you open it for the first time there's a lot of information but the user doesn't know where it comes from
* create panel should be improved -&gt; create space is in the wrong place
* treeview navigation is confusing, it's hard to understand its logic right now
* information about comments, attachments, history to put at the top of the page? -&gt; nobody sees them

=== Consistency ===

* same skin for the administration as for everything else
* unify the looks of the edit and view mode
** in-place editing
** same place, same configuration, nothing different but the edit

== Configuration &amp; Administration ==

=== Configuration ===

* first interaction -&gt; first thing the user sees when the homepage is displayed -&gt; display additional information for the first time -&gt; steps you have to do to configure your wiki. Basic steps required to make your wiki work. Popup?
* hidden pages / spaces -&gt; all pages in the space are hidden = hidden space?

=== Administration ===

* New spaces appear once I've logged in as an Admin. Why?
* Create accounts for new users -&gt; I don't really know where to go. 
* What is the order of icons in the administration? Why is it like that?
** Explanatations for each item in administration (captions, tooltips)
** Why OpenOffice? What is it doing here? It's an option.
** Registration is confusing
* Administration: drop-down &amp; "Show available categories" button put together. Why is that so?
** The drop-down menu isn't self-explanatory, it doesn't tell anything about itself
** "Add new user" should be at the top of the page
** Clicking on "Create new user" launches a popup -&gt; various interaction styles
*** what's mandatory, what's optional?
*** no error messages, information gets lost
*** email field not used by default
*** automatically generate a password for the user (-&gt; invitation manager)
*** configuring registration options / process in XWiki in complicated
*** **email addresses are hidden in the user profile**
*** user profile -&gt; actions are not in the right place
** put user into a group
*** group names suck, system groups are not identified as such
*** edit button -&gt; what am I editing, group name of group members? Right now renaming a group will break configured rights
*** on a group page -&gt; "add user to group" button
*** local &amp; global users -&gt; what does that mean on a standard XE instance?
** configuring rights
*** rights inheritance
*** it's dangerous to change XWikiAllGroup and XWikiAdminGroup rights yet it can be done easily
*** the deny warning is painful
*** select the rights you want and then apply them -&gt; make the rights transactional (button to save)
*** revert rights to the default setting button
*** describe every right and explain how to set them
* sometimes configuration cannot be achieved but through objects -&gt; an interface should always be available to make this explicit
** hide technical pages even from admin, the admin shouldn't see everything -&gt; like in windows, let people see / hide hidden documents

== Help ==

* Add an "Help" panel between Search and Quick Links
* Make the link to the user guide more obvious
* Contextual help
* Make the help more obvious
** when there's only one user in the wiki, display all the help, message disappears once another user has been created
* make the user guide easier to find, it cannot be found easily right now

== Language ==

* Create language-specific distribution
** Select the language from the installer
** Choose the language of your wiki from the installer
* translations are painful and confusing to setup -&gt; hard to find, hard to set, translations don't appear in all pages at once, when on a given page it's hard to know in which languages it has been translated.
** lack of feedback when setting up translations</content>
</xwikidoc>
