<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xwikidoc>
  <web>AdminGuide</web>
  <name>AccessWiki</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <parent>WebHome</parent>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <customClass/>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <creationDate>1319531353000</creationDate>
  <date>1360853350000</date>
  <contentUpdateDate>1360853350000</contentUpdateDate>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>Access a wiki</title>
  <template/>
  <defaultTemplate/>
  <validationScript/>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.0</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <content>By default when you connect to your wiki farm you will go to the main wiki. To be able to access other wikis, XWiki supports two modes.

{{toc/}}

= The domain name based wiki access =

{{info}}
This was the default mode until XWiki 3.3 RC1. After the release of XWiki Enterprise 3.3 RC1, the URL path based access mode is used as default.
{{/info}}

By default this mode is disabled. To enable it, go to ##xwiki.cfg## and set //xwiki.virtual.usepath// to 0.

In virtual mode you can access any wiki by the [[domain name/alias&gt;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System]] registered in its descriptor with the field ##server## ("Alias" in the UI).

For example if the url is //{{{http://wikiname.xwiki.org/xwiki/bin/view/Space/Page}}}// XWiki will try to find "wikiname.xwiki.org" as a value of the ##server## field in the objects of class ##XWiki.XWikiServerClass##. Then it extracts the last part of the page name to get the wiki identifier: in this case it finds ##XWiki.XWikiServerWikiname## and extracts "wikiname" as the wiki identifier to set the database to query on.
 
If no descriptor can be found:

* if the host is an IP (127.0.0.1, 85.65.12.36, etc.) XWiki selects the main wiki
* else, if the first part of the host name (what is before the first point) is "www" XWiki selects the main wiki
* else, if the first part of the host name matches a wiki identifier XWiki selects that wiki

If after all no wiki has been found, then XWiki redirects to the URL configured in the property ##xwiki.virtual.redirect## of ##xwiki.cfg##.

So to be able to access your wiki you need to configure your DNS or modify hosts file in your operating system (see [[Hosts file documentation on Wikipedia&gt;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hosts_file]] for details).

= The URL path based wiki access =

{{info}}
* This mode is supported only since XWiki Platform 1.7 and XWiki Enterprise Manager 1.5 and only when enabled.
* Starting with XWiki 3.3 RC1, this is the default mode.
{{/info}}

When this mode is enabled you can access a wiki using an url like: {{{http://host/xwiki/wiki/wikialias/view/Space/Page}}}.
The two parts of ##/wiki/wikialias## mean:

* ##wiki##: this is used by XWiki to identify the URL as a URL path based multiwiki access. You can configure it in ##xwiki.cfg## with the property ##xwiki.virtual.usepath.servletpath##.
(((
{{warning}}
Don't forget to set the ##xwiki.authentication.logoutpage## property accordingly. Change the "wiki" part in the property value for the right alias.
{{/warning}}
)))
* ##wikialias##: this is used by XWiki to find the wiki descriptor
** first it tries to match ##wikialias## with the descriptors 
** if it can't find the descriptor this way it tries to match the wiki descriptor using ##wikialias## as the wiki identifier. This means looking whether the ##XWiki.XWikiServerWikialias## document exists and contains an object of the ##XWiki.XWikiServerClass## class</content>
</xwikidoc>
