<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xwikidoc>
  <web>AdminGuide</web>
  <name>InstallationHSQL</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <parent>AdminGuide.Installation</parent>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <customClass/>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <creationDate>1165866978000</creationDate>
  <date>1360950257000</date>
  <contentUpdateDate>1360950257000</contentUpdateDate>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>HSQLDB Installation</title>
  <template/>
  <defaultTemplate/>
  <validationScript/>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.1</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <object>
    <class>
      <name>XWiki.TagClass</name>
      <customClass/>
      <customMapping/>
      <defaultViewSheet/>
      <defaultEditSheet/>
      <defaultWeb/>
      <nameField/>
      <validationScript/>
      <tags>
        <cache>0</cache>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayType>input</displayType>
        <multiSelect>1</multiSelect>
        <name>tags</name>
        <number>1</number>
        <prettyName>Tags</prettyName>
        <relationalStorage>1</relationalStorage>
        <separator>|</separator>
        <separators>|,</separators>
        <size>30</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <values/>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StaticListClass</classType>
      </tags>
    </class>
    <name>AdminGuide.InstallationHSQL</name>
    <number>0</number>
    <className>XWiki.TagClass</className>
    <guid>fe700abe-ccf2-4b55-b212-1cb4fe89f7ad</guid>
    <property>
      <tags/>
    </property>
  </object>
  <content>Follow these instructions:

* HSQLDB is a very simple database to configure as you don't need to install nor to start it before being able to use it. It comes as a single JAR file named ##hsqldb*.jar##. If your XWiki WAR doesn't have it in ##WEB-INF/lib## you'll need to download it and copy it there. You can download it from the [[HSQLDB web site&gt;&gt;http://hsqldb.org/]] or directly from the [[Maven Central Repository&gt;&gt;http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/hsqldb/hsqldb/]].
* Once this is done, you need to configure XWiki to use HSQLDB and to tell it where the database files will be created. To do this, edit the ##WEB-INF/hibernate.cfg.xml## file where you have expanded the XWiki WAR file and uncommented the HSQLDB part.

{{warning}}
If you intend to use HSQLDB in production you should probably tune it for a production usage. If you've installed the XWiki standalone distribution just be aware that it's not tuned to be production-ready. Also note that you would need to find a way to perform backups, live replication, administration tools etc. We would suggest using a more production-ready database such as MySQL or PostgreSQL if you can.
{{/warning}}

= Other optional ideas =

* You can use a remote HSQLDB database instead of embedding it. To do this, just use a URL like ##jdbc:hsqldb:hsql:HOSTNAME...## instead of the ##jdbcc:hsqldb:file:..## URL. The major version of the hsqldb jar file must match the major version that the HSQLDB server is using.
* If you want to use your app server facilities to manage your data sources (generally a better strategy), then you must follow these steps:
** Put the ##hsqldb*.jar## file into your app server class path instead of in your web app (like in ##$CATALINA_HOME/common/lib##)
** In ##hibernate.cfg.xml##, use the following settings in place of the HSQLDB block in the sample file. Specifically, do not set the url, user, etc. here and leave the provider_class unset (i.e. use the default value), since XWiki's implementation does not handle container-managed data sources:
{{code}}
&lt;property name="connection.datasource"&gt;java:/comp/env/jdbc/xwiki&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="dialect"&gt;org.hibernate.dialect.HSQLDialect&lt;/property&gt;
{{/code}}
** the final step is to manage the data source using app server facilities. With Tomcat, for example, you would map the //resource link// ##jcbc/xwikiDs## to a container-managed data source using the Admin web app or by editing the file ##conf/Catalina/*/xwiki.xml## (i.e. webapp-name + ".xml").</content>
</xwikidoc>
