<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<xwikidoc>
  <web>AdminGuide</web>
  <name>Virtualization</name>
  <language/>
  <defaultLanguage/>
  <translation>0</translation>
  <parent>AdminGuide.WebHome</parent>
  <creator>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</creator>
  <author>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</author>
  <customClass/>
  <contentAuthor>xwiki:XWiki.Admin</contentAuthor>
  <creationDate>1169721304000</creationDate>
  <date>1360950253000</date>
  <contentUpdateDate>1360950253000</contentUpdateDate>
  <version>1.1</version>
  <title>Creating a Multi-tenant environment</title>
  <template/>
  <defaultTemplate/>
  <validationScript/>
  <comment/>
  <minorEdit>false</minorEdit>
  <syntaxId>xwiki/2.0</syntaxId>
  <hidden>false</hidden>
  <object>
    <class>
      <name>XWiki.TagClass</name>
      <customClass/>
      <customMapping/>
      <defaultViewSheet/>
      <defaultEditSheet/>
      <defaultWeb/>
      <nameField/>
      <validationScript/>
      <tags>
        <cache>0</cache>
        <disabled>0</disabled>
        <displayType>input</displayType>
        <multiSelect>1</multiSelect>
        <name>tags</name>
        <number>1</number>
        <prettyName>Tags</prettyName>
        <relationalStorage>1</relationalStorage>
        <separator>|</separator>
        <separators>|,</separators>
        <size>30</size>
        <unmodifiable>0</unmodifiable>
        <values/>
        <classType>com.xpn.xwiki.objects.classes.StaticListClass</classType>
      </tags>
    </class>
    <name>AdminGuide.Virtualization</name>
    <number>0</number>
    <className>XWiki.TagClass</className>
    <guid>9dae1472-81fb-4a7f-b2d2-f9731039effb</guid>
    <property>
      <tags/>
    </property>
  </object>
  <content>{{box cssClass="floatinginfobox" title="**Contents**"}}{{toc/}}{{/box}}

A [[multi-tenant&gt;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multitenancy]] setup (a.k.a "virtual mode", "multi-wiki" or "farm mode") allows you to have several wikis running on the same XWiki instance (i.e. in the same JVM).

Each wiki has its own database schema, thus allowing for a complete data separation between the different wikis in the same instance.

The main advantage of multi-tenancy is performance optimization. A single XWiki instance on a physical machine (thus a single Servlet Container) will perform much better than having several XWiki instances running on the same machine, which wouldn't scale. As an example known XWiki multi-tenant instances host several thousands hundreds to several thousands wikis on a single XWiki instance.

= Requirements =

The multi-tenancy feature currently works only on some databases:
* Databases known to work are: MySQL, Oracle and HSQLDB (starting with XWiki 4.3M1)
* PostgreSQL is currently not supported as the JDBC driver doesn't support setCatalog() for changing databases. That's because PostgreSQL connections are pointed to a specific database at connection time (see jira issue [[XWIKI-1960&gt;&gt;http://jira.xwiki.org/jira/browse/XWIKI-1960]])
* [[Derby is currently not supported&gt;&gt;http://jira.xwiki.org/browse/XWIKI-8244]]

In addition to having a supported database you'll also need:
* Choosing one instance of XWiki that has been installed on your network. The database name for this wiki should be ##xwiki##. If you've still got to install the XWiki instance, please refer to [[the installation guide&gt;&gt;AdminGuide.Installation]] and install XWiki Enterprise first
* Admin privileges on this XWiki instance
* You need to be sure that the ##xwiki## user used to create the main database has the correct permissions to be able to create other schemas since each subwiki will create a new database schema
* You need to be able to restart the java container (e.g. Tomcat or Jetty), or can have this restarted on demand.
** The ##xwiki.cfg## file will also have to be modified, so you will need to have write access to this file on the server

= Set up =

* Stop your XWiki instance, edit the ##WEB-INF/xwiki.cfg## file, look for the ##xwiki.virtual## property and set it to ##1##: {{code}}xwiki.virtual=1{{/code}}
* Restart your XWiki instance
* Install the [[Wiki Manager Application&gt;&gt;extensions:Extension.Wiki Manager Application]]

Starting with XWiki Enterprise 3.3 you can easily install the Wiki Manager Application using the Extension Manager by following these steps:
* Go to the administration page and click on "Add Extensions" under "Extension Manager"
* Click on "Advanced search" and enter the following information:
** extension id: ##org.xwiki.platform:xwiki-platform-wiki-manager-ui##
** extension version: ##4.3## (adapt to the version you wish to install; make it match the version of the XWiki Enterprise you're using)
* Click "Search"
* Click "Install"
* Click "Apply"
* Verify that the Wiki Manager extension is correctly installed by navigating to the [[WikiManager WebHome page&gt;&gt;http://localhost:8080/xwiki/bin/view/WikiManager/WebHome]] which should now exist

You now have a multi-tenant installation and can proceed to use the [[Wiki Manager Application&gt;&gt;extensions:Extension.Wiki Manager Application]] to create subwikis.</content>
</xwikidoc>
